Guide to the John R. TeWinkel papers, 1926-1991.
TeWinkel, John R. papers, 1926-1991.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
John R. TeWinkel papers, 1926-1991.
4380
John R. TeWinkel, 1916-
1.9 cubic ft.
Correspondence; notes, flashcards, and other materials related to linguistics and spelling reform; files; an autobiography and vitae; a will; news clippings; and photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers of John R. TeWinkel, a Cornell graduate who lived in China, Morocco, Greece, Nigeria, and the United States.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
John R. TeWinkel graduated from Cornell University in 1938 and received an M.A. from Boston University in 1958. From 1941 to 1942, he taught English in Nanking and Chungking, China, and later taught in Morocco, Greece, and Nigeria, as well as in a number of schools in the United States. He also served in a Friends Ambulance Unit as a medical relief distributor in South China, 1942-1944; and as librarian and transaction clerk in the UN Relief and Rehabilitation Administration headquarters in Washington, D.C.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers include correspondence; notes, flashcards, and other materials related to linguistics and spelling reform; files on health, travels, social planning, arms control, and other topics; an autobiography and vitae; a will; news clippings; and photographs. Correspondents include siblings W. Gordon, Helen, Lois, and Joy TeWinkel; his aunt, Sarella TeWinkel; his mother, Lucy TeWinkel; Idorenyin U. Akpan; David Sergeant; and others, especially friends in Australia and Nigeria. Also, memorabilia relating to his tour of Japan, 1988; and correspondence about Sichuan University. Also, a broadside "Letter from the Communist Party to the Whole People," an explanation of military suppression in Tiananmen Square, 1989.
A May 7, 1982 letter to Tewinkel covers gay and lesbian topics, including gay sex in Sydney, Australia's steam baths, Radclyffe Hall's "The Well of Loneliness," and other literature on homosexuality. (Box 1, folder 6)
SUBJECTS
Names:
TeWinkel, John R., 1916-; Akpan, Idorenyin U.; Sergeant, David.; TeWinkel, Helen.; TeWinkel, Joy.; TeWinkel, Lois.; TeWinkel, Lucy.; TeWinkel, Sarella.; TeWinkel, W. Gordon.
Subjects:
Spelling reform.; Phonetic alphabet.; New Age movement.; Arms control.; Tian'an Men (Beijing, China).
Places:
Africa--Description and travel.; Nigeria--Description and travel.; China--Description and travel.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Letter to Shen Xiaoquian is closed until 2015.
CONTAINER LIST
- TeWinkel family letters, 1930-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- TeWinkel family letters, Jan.-Sept. 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- TeWinkel family letters, Oct.-Dec. 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- TeWinkel family letters, 1940, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- John TeWinkel letters to family, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- David Sergeant letters, Australia, 1967-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Nigerian letters, 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Nigerian letters, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Idorenyin U. Akpan, Nigeria, c. 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- General correspondence, 1935-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- General correspondence, 1957-1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- General correspondence, 1975-1988, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Miscellany, 1944, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
- John TeWinkel letters to family, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- John TeWinkel letters to family, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- John TeWinkel letters to family, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- John TeWinkel letters to family, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- John TeWinkel letters to family, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- John TeWinkel letters to family, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
- Travel documents (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Autobiography - Berkeley, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Autobiographical sketch, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Vitae, 1933-1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Will and clippings (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Applications, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Edgar Cayce (Box 2, Folder 6)
- General correspondence, 1944-1961, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Bibliography (Box 2, Folder 8)
- College bluebooks (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Corbett, Jim - articles (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Africa, 1958-1971 (Box 2, Folder 11-14)
- Ing (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Linguistics (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Reading and Unifon (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Rupert, Arnold (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
- Rit (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Spelwel (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Spel. Ref. (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Spelling - William W. Murphy (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Chinese flash cards (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Alternative thought miscellany (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
- Appaloosa horse (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Sketch of Aristotle painting, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Arms control (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Articles and news clippings (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Base community (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Borsadi (Box 3, Folder 9)
- China geography (Box 3, Folder 10)
- University of Massachusetts - Chinese lessons, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Community economics, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Counselors manual, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Cultural survival (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Currency (Box 3, Folder 15)
- "Defense Monitor" (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Ekistics, social planning, and miscellany (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Finances in Mexico and Quito, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Health (Box 3, Folder 19)
- "Hiland Vali Apresiation", 1983 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Hippocrates Health Institute (Box 3, Folder 21)
- "How Old is the Earth?" (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Human economy (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Hunger, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Hypoglycemia, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Japan, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Japanese education, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Land, 1946-1951 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Macroanalysis seminars, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Maps (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Medical advances, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Medicare (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Micah 6:8 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Miracles, Course in (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Miscellany, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Miscellany, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Morocco, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- National Gay Lesbian Task Force (NGLTF) (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Neanderthal man (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Nigeria, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Nuclear war, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Peace plan for Europe, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- People's Yellow Pages, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Psychology (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Quakers, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Quaker concerns, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Rainforest, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Reprints (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Right sharing; debt, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Rupert, Arnold, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Senior Aide Handbook, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Seventh Generation Fund, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- Sleep (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Sleep clinic, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Spanish (Box 3, Folder 55)
- Survival of tribes, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 56)
- Teaching in China Preparation Committee, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Thresholds - Manual for the Correctional Counselor, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 58-59)
- Umskrip (Box 3, Folder 60)
- Wildlife (Box 3, Folder 61)
- Miscellaneous correspondence and other papers, ca. 1950's-1990's (Box 4)
- "Letter from the Communist Party to the Whole People," an explanation of military suppression in Tiananmen Square, 1989 (Folder MSS Box 88)